Guide to the James H. Pou Bailey Papers, 1901-1970 RL.00064
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James H. Pou Bailey papers
1901-1970
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bailey, James Hinton Pou, 1917-
RL.00064
14.6 Linear Feet
8,640 items
Access Restrictions
The Law Practices: Client Files Series (boxes 8-22) are closed for 75 years after the last date of creation for files in the series (1966). The series will be reviewed in 2041.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The bulk of the James H. Pou Bailey Papers was given to Duke University in 1983 by Bailey. In 1977, one item was purchased for the collection. Copyright interests in these papers have not been transferred to the University.
Biographical Note
Missing Title
1917, Aug. 14 Born, Baltimore, MD
1940 B.A., University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
1941 L.L.B., University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and admitted to the bar
1941-1942 Special Agent, Federal Bureau of Investigation
1942-1945 Served in the United States Army, attaining the rank of Captain
1944-1945 Served in the European theater of World War II
1945, Aug. 1 Married Marie Fiquet Pate
1946 Entered law practice of Bailey & Bailey in Raleigh, N.C., with his father, Josiah W. Bailey
1947 Father died and Bailey began to practice law alone
1948 Unsuccessful candidate for North Carolina State Senate
1950 Elected to North Carolina Senate, 13th Senatorial District, Wake County
1952 Reelected to the North Carolina Senate from the 13th Senatorial District, Wake County
1953-1965 Served as general counsel to the North Carolina Bankers' Association
1954-1962 Entered law practice of Bailey & Bason in Raleigh, N.C.
1962-1965 Entered law practice of Bailey & Ragsdale in Raleigh, N.C.
1965, July 9 Appointed Judge of the Superior Court, 10th Judicial District of North Carolina
1966 Elected to unexpired term as judge
1968 Marie F. P. Bailey died
1972, June 3 Married Ann Thomas
1972 Elected to full term as judge
1985, July Retired from the bench.
Bailey held leadership positions in a variety of civic and professional organizations, among them the American Red Cross, the Raleigh Chamber of Commerce, the Raleigh Traffic Safety Council, the North Carolina Amvets, the North Carolina Boy Scouts, and the Wake County Bar Association.
As a state senator, Bailey served as chair of the Interstate Federal Relations and Judiciary committees. Bailey has two sons, James H. Pou Bailey II and Edwin Pate Bailey.
Collection Overview
The James H. Pou Bailey Papers span the years 1901 to 1970 with the bulk of the papers dating from 1948 to 1965. The Law Practices: Clients Series (CLOSED), which contains papers relating to specific clients in his law practice, comprises the bulk of the collection. The papers also document Bailey's political interests and pursuit of political office, financial and legal matters pertaining to himself and family members, and his involvement in civic organizations. These concerns are documented by the Correspondence, Subject Files, Legal and Financial Papers, and Writings and Speeches Series. While the collection contains a few speeches to various organizations and civic groups, there are not as many as one might expect from a person who ran for the North Carolina State Senate three times and held the office for two terms (four years). Also, there are not many papers relating to his tenure as Judge of Superior Court from the 10th Judicial District.
The business and financial climate in North Carolina during the late 1940s to the early 1960s may be studied through the Law Practices: Clients (CLOSED) and Subject Files Series. Early efforts to promote cable television in North Carolina (1963-1964) through the Engineering Sales Corporation of Raleigh, N.C. and to encourage the use of natural gas in North Carolina (1955-1959) through the efforts of consulting engineers, Porter, Barry, & Associates of Baton Rouge, La. are delineated in this series. Both firms were legal clients of Bailey.
Of particular note are several political figures represented in the Correspondence Series, including North Carolina Senator Willis Smith and Virginia Senator Harry F. Byrd. The business, professional, and personal relationship of Bailey with United States Senator from North Carolina, Jesse Helms, is reflected in the Correspondence and Law Practices: Clients Series (CLOSED). The papers particularly concern Helms's position as administrative assistant to Senator Willis Smith and the offices Helms held in the North Carolina Bankers Association (NCBA), a Bailey client. Information about policies and laws affecting banks in North Carolina are also represented in the Law Practices: Clients Series (CLOSED). The Subject Files Series contains Bailey's Senatorial Papers (1950-1954). Included is constituent mail, information pertaining to political appointments, and his service on various committees, including his chairmanship of the Interstate and Federal Relations and Judiciary Committees.
The Subject Files and Legal and Financial Papers Series disclose some of the financial interests held by Bailey and his family. Most notable are their interest in the Andrew Johnson Hotel in Raleigh, N.C. and Bailey's interest in a 360 acre farm in Johnston County, N.C. Included is information relating to the management of both enterprises. The collection also highlights father-son relationships in the correspondence between Josiah W. Bailey and James H. Pou Bailey and between James H. Pou Bailey and his son, Jim. (Correspondence Series).
The Josiah W. Bailey (Bailey's father) Papers is a related collection in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Banks and banking -- North Carolina; Fathers and sons; North Carolina -- Economic conditions; Domestic relations -- North Carolina -- Cases; Farm Management -- North Carolina -- Johnston County; Hotel management -- North Carolina -- Raleigh; Gas, Natural -- North Carolina; Cable television -- North Carolina; Judicial power -- North Carolina; North Carolina -- Politics and government; Intergovernmental tax relations -- North Carolina; Lawyers -- North Carolina; Intergovernmental fiscal relations -- North Carolina; Commercial law -- North Carolina; Andrew Johnson Hotel (Raleigh, N.C.); Smith, Willis, 1887-1953; Porter, Barry and Associates (Baton Rouge, La.); North Carolina. General Assembly. Senate; North Carolina Bankers Association; Helms, Jesse; Engineering Sales Corporation (Raleigh, N.C.); Byrd, Harry Flood, 1887-1966; Bailey, Josiah William, 1873-1946
- Correspondence Series, 1926-1967 and undated, 1,680 items; 2.8 linear ft
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes personal, business, and political correspondence. There is some overlap between correspondence in this series and that located in the Subject Files: Politics Series.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged primarily in chronological order, with the exception that the correspondence of Bailey's father, Senator Josiah W. Bailey, is in a separate file.
  - 1940-1951, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - 1952-1954, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - 1955-1959, Aug., 6 folders (Box 3)
  - 1959-Sept.-1963, 7 folders (Box 4)
  - 1964-1967, undated, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Bailey, Josiah W., 1926-1943, 6 folders (Box 6)
  - Bailey, Josiah W., 1944-1946, 7 folders (Box 7)
- Law Practices: Clients Series (CLOSED), 1947-1966., 3,600 items; 6 linear ft.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  The Law Practices: Client Files Series (boxes 8-22) are closed for 75 years after the last date of creation for files in the series (1966). This restriction will be reviewed in 2041.
  Primarily correspondence, legal and financial papers, clippings, and handwritten notes pertaining to law clients of Bailey. The series is divided into two sections: business and domestic relations cases. Incorporated companies comprise the bulk of the business clients, while the domestic relations cases primarily consist of divorce and child custody suits.
  Each section is arranged in alphabetical order by name of client. However, because of the amount of material for some business clients, the papers for some are further subdivided.
  - B-E, 1948-1966 and undated (Box 8)
  - E-K, 1952-1964 and undated (Box 9)
  - K-N, 1948-1961 and undated (Box 10)
  - N, 1955-1959 (Box 11)
  - N, 1959-1963 (Box 12)
  - N, 1951-1966 and undated (Box 13)
  - N, 1951-1965 and undated (Box 14)
  - N, 1951-1965 and undated (Box 15)
  - N-P, 1887-1962 and undated (Box 16)
  - P, 1947-1960 and undated (Box 17)
  - P, 1956-1957 (Box 18)
  - P-W and Miscellaneous, 1922-1966 and undated (Box 19)
- Law Practices: Clients: Domestic Relations Series (CLOSED)
  Conditions Governing Access
  - A-H, 1947-1961 and undated (Box 20)
  - H-N, 1951-1966 and undated (Box 21)
  - N-W and Miscellaneous, 1946-1964 (Box 22)
- Subject Files Series, 1947-1970., 2,880 items; 4.8 linear ft.
  Correspondence, legal and financial papers, press releases, and newsclippings relating to civic, political, and professional organizations. Also includes papers concerning political campaigns, Bailey's career, and some of his financial interests.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of organization or topic. Large files are divided into subgroups.
  - Andrew Johnson Hotel: (Box 23)
    - Correspondence, 1947-1964, 5 folders (Box 23)
    - Legal Papers, 1945-1964, undated, 2 folders (Box 24)
    - Financial Papers, 1948-1961, 3 folders (Box 24)
    - Financial Papers (Box 25)
      - 1962-1965, undated (Box 25)
      - Monthly statements, 1950-1959, 4 folders (Box 25)
    - Financial Papers: (Box 26)
      - Monthly statements, 1960-1962 (Box 26)
      - Insurance and Inspection Records, 1951-1964, undated, 2 folders (Box 26)
      - Consultants' Reports, 1957-1961, undated (Box 26)
    - Plans, Specifications, etc., undated (Box 26)
  - Hoover Commission, 1949-1950 (Box 27)
  - Institute of Religion, 1956 (Box 27)
  - Johnston Co. Farm, 1946-1959, 4 folders (Box 27)
  - Johnston Co. Farm, 1960-1962, undated (Box 28)
  - Judicial Papers:
    - Correspondence, 1965, July-1966, 2 folders (Box 28)
    - Miscellaneous, 1965-1970 (Box 28)
  - Legislative Matters: Micellaneous, 1949-1963, undated (Box 28)
  - Organizations:
    - American Red Cross, 1950 (Box 28)
    - Capital City Club, Inc., 1961-1964, undated (Box 28)
  - Organizations: (Box 29)
    - Chamber of Commerce, 1947-1963, undated, 2 folders (Box 29)
    - Civil Defense, 1952-1953, undated (Box 29)
    - General Statutes Commission, 1953-1959, undated (Box 29)
    - Kiwanis Club, 1963-1964, undated (Box 29)
    - N.C. Amvets, 1946-1953, undated (Box 29)
    - N.C. Boy Scouts, 1946-1962, undated (Box 29)
    - Raleigh Ports Authority, 1957 (Box 29)
  - Organizations: (Box 30)
    - Terpsichorean Club, 1949, undated (Box 30)
    - Wake County Bar Association--Legal Aid Committee, 1947-1965, undated (Box 30)
    - Young Democrats Club, 1946-1953 (Box 30)
    - Miscellaneous, 1948-1963 (Box 30)
  - Outer Banks Project, 1952 (Box 30)
  - Politics:
    - Campaigns:
      - J.H.P. Bailey, 1948-1952, undated, 4 folders (Box 30)
      - Mallard-Morris, 1968, undated (Box 30)
  - Politics: (Box 31)
    - Campaigns:
      - Dan K. Moore, 1964, undated (Box 31)
      - George Wallace for President, 1964, undated (Box 31)
      - Miscellaneous, 1951-1964 (Box 31)
      - Proposed Candidacy for U. S. Congress (J.H.P. Bailey vs. Harold Cooley), 1956, undated (Box 31)
    - Senatorial papers:
      - Correspondence, 1950, Oct.-1951, July, 3 folders (Box 31)
  - Politics: (Box 32)
    - Senatorial papers:
      - Correspondence, 1951-1954, undated, 3 folders (Box 32)
      - Appointments, 1952-1953 (Box 32)
      - Auto Inspection Bill-- Inaugural Committee (Box 32)
  - Politics: (Box 33)
    - Senatorial papers:
      - Interstate and Federal regulations, 1953-1954, undated, 3 folders (Box 33)
      - Judiciary Committee, 1953 (Box 33)
      - Libraries-- Minimum Wage, 1953 (Box 33)
      - N.C. State Taxes, 1952-1953 (Box 33)
      - Raleigh, N.C., 1951-1953 (Box 33)
      - State employees-- Sunday auto racing, 1951-1953 (Box 33)
  - Politics: (Box 34)
    - Senatorial papers:
      - United States Forces for Education, 1953 (Box 34)
      - Miscellaneous, 1950-1964, 2 folders (Box 34)
  - Race Relations, 1951-1958, undated (Box 34)
  - Raleigh, N.C., 1946-1960, undated (Box 34)
  - U.S. Attorney for the Eastern District, N.C.--proposed appt. of James H. Pou Bailey, 1961 (Box 34)
  - Woodberry Forest School, 1941-1964, undated (Box 34)
- Legal and Financial Papers Series, 1901-1966 and undated, 275 items; 0.5 linear ft.
  Correspondence, leases, wills, deeds, receipts, and other financial papers primarily pertaining to the settlement of estates of Bailey relatives, both maternal (Pou) and paternal, (Bailey) family members.
  Files are arranged by name of family member or family.
  - Bailey Family, 1947-1952 (Box 35)
  - Bailey, James H. Pou:
    - 1945-1960 (Box 35)
    - Raleigh Union Bus Station Trust, 1960-1961 (Box 35)
  - Bailey, Josiah W., 1929-1952 (Box 35)
  - Pou Family, 1901-1966, undated, 2 folders (Box 35)
  - Pou, Martha (Mattie), 1939-1949 (Box 36)
- Writings and Speeches, 1948-1960 and undated, 175 items; 0.3 linear ft.
  Chiefly typewritten copies of the column, Raleigh Roundup, which appeared in 36 small town newspapers throughout North Carolina with Bailey's picture and name. Includes reader correspondence relating to the column. Also contains a few speeches Bailey made before various groups.
  Subdivided into two subgroups: speeches he made before organizations and the rest relating to the Raleigh Roundup column.
  - 1948-1960, undated (Box 36)
  - Raleigh Round-Up, 1950-1952, undated, 4 folders (Box 36)
- Miscellaneous Series, 1941-1969 and undated, 30 items; 0.2 linear ft.
  Certificates, clippings, and photographs primarily relating to Bailey.
  Photographs are undated and are arranged at the end of the other miscellaneous items.
  - 1941-1969, undated (Box 37)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 37)
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box 37)
- Oversize Materials Series
  - Law Practices: Clients and Subject Files series (CLOSED) (Oversize-folder Sec. A OV13)
  - Law Cases: Clients and Subject Files series (CLOSED) (Oversize-folder 2)